Register of the Scientists For Sakharov, Orlov And Shcharansky Records, 1975-2010
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1973-1998.
  - Shcharansky, Natan (Anatoly B.) and Avital. See also Subject File/Bay Area Council on Soviet Jewry
    - Messages (Folder 21)
    - Newsletters (Folder 22)
    - Press releases (Folder 23)
    - Printed matter (Folder 24)
    - Reports (Folder 25)
    - Schedule (Folder 26)
    - Statements (Folder 27)
    - Telegrams (Folder 28)
    - Miscellany (Folder 29)
  - Siegelman, Philip
    - Correspondence
      - Undated (Folder 30)
      - Includes a letter to Emily J. Flory, 1979-1985. (Folder 31)
      - 1986-1998 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda (Folder 2)
    - Statements (Folder 3)
    - Telegrams (Folder 4)
  - Soviet Union (Folder 5)
  - Union of Councils for Soviet Jews (Folder 6-14)
  - United States. Congress. Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe
    - General (Folder 15)
    - Brochures (Folder 16)
    - Bulletins (Folder 17)
    - Clippings (Folder 18)
    - Conference proceedings (Folder 19)
    - Correspondence (Folder 20)
    - List of members for the U.S. delegation to the Madrid Conference (Folder 21)
    - Memoranda (Folder 22)
    - Minutes of meetings (Folder 23)
    - Newsletters (Folder 24)
    - Press conferences (Folder 25)
    - Printed matter (Folder 26)
    - Remarks by Max M. Kampelman, Chairman U.S. delegation (Folder 27)
    - Reports (Box 31)
      - 1979 (Folder 1)
      - 1980-1983 (Folder 2)
    - Statements. Includes statements by Dante B. Fascell, Philip Handler, Max M. Kampelman, Thomas R. Pickering, and Frank Press (Folder 3)
    - Testimony by Duane Acker, President, Kansas State University (Folder 4)
  - World Affairs Council (Folder 5)
  - World Without War Council (Folder 6)
  - Miscellany (Folder 7)
- Writing by Others, 1975-1994
  Articles written by others arranged alphabetically by name
  - Adelman, Kenneth L. (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Adelstein, Robert (Folder 9)
  - Adler-Karlsson, Gunnar (Folder 10)
  - Amaldi, Edoardo (Folder 11)
  - Anfinsen, Christian B. and others (Folder 12)
  - Bethe, Hans A. and Kurt Gottfried (Folder 13)
  - Brie, Rita La and Andrew M. Sessler (Folder 14)
  - Bukovsky, Vladimir (Folder 15)
  - Davis, Moshe (Folder 16)
  - DeWitt, Hugh E. (Folder 17)
  - Dorodnitsyn, Anatoly and others (Folder 18)
  - Dowty, Alan (Folder 19)
  - Friedlander, E. (Folder 20)
  - Gaer, Felice D. See also Subject File/Science -International cooperation (Folder 21)
  - Gershman, Carl (Folder 22)
  - Goldman, Marvin (Folder 23)
  - Goldwasser, Edwin L. and Francis E. Low (Folder 24)
  - Ispirien, Karo Asadouri (Folder 25)
  - Keefe, Dennis (Folder 26)
  - Kirkpatrick, Jean (Folder 27)
  - Lefever, Ernest W. See also Subject File/Human rights (Folder 28)
  - Levine, H. B. (Folder 29)
  - Lewis, Anthony (Folder 30)
  - Livinoff, Emanuel (Folder 31)
  - Lwoff, André (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Medvedev, Grigorii (Folder 2)
  - Miller, Larisa (Folder 3)
  - Minker, Jack (Folder 4)
  - Oshins, Eddie (Folder 5)
  - Ovchinnikov, Yu (Folder 6)
  - Petit, Charles (Folder 7)
  - Popovsky, Mark (Folder 8)
  - Schapira, Morey (Folder 9)
  - Shakhnazarov, G. (Folder 10)
  - Taskar, Michael (Folder 11)
  - Taylor, Howard (Folder 12)
  - Toohig, Timothy (Folder 13)
  - Turchin, Valentine (Folder 14)
  - Unsöld, Albrecht (Folder 15)
  - Wade, Nicholas (Folder 16)
  - Wilson, Richard (Folder 17)
  - Wisse, Ruth R. (Folder 18)
  - Yanai, Yakov (Folder 19)
  - Yanov, Alexander (Folder 20)
  - Yim, Man-Sung and John S. Evans (Folder 21)
  - Zinoviev, Alexander (Folder 22)
  - Various authors, Berkeley Labs Research Review, 1998 (Folder 23)
- Index Cards
  Index cards with addresses of various individuals and organizations, arranged alphabetically by name
  Cards with addresses of various individuals and organizations
- Memorabilia, n.d.
  Bank stamp and pin with the SOS logo
  - Bank of America stamp for SOS deposits (Box 33)
  - Pin with the SOS logo
- Oversize file, 1975-1990
  Computer-generated address lists, enlarged photocopy of Yuri Orlov, issue of Pravda, posters, prints and graphics design layout sheets for SOS advertisements, printed matter, and proclamations, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Computer-generated address lists (Box 34)
  - Computer-generated address lists (Box 35)
  - Enlarged photocopy of a photograph of Yuri Orlov
  - Issue of Pravda, 1975 August 2
  - Overhead slides
    - Two clippings from the San Francisco Chronicle, 1981-1986
    - Unidentified photograph, n.d.
  - Posters of Elena Bonner announcing her visit and details about her talks on human rights and medical care in the Soviet Union, University of California, Berkeley,; and one poster of Andrei Sakharov, 1990 March 22 and 23
  - Printed matter
  - Proclamations issued by Ronald Reagan
    - "Captive Nations Week," Includes a letter from the White House, 1984.
    - "Human Rights, Bill of Rights Day, and Human Rights Week,", 1987
  - 8 negative sheets depicting Andrei Sakharov, Yuri Orlov, and Natan (Anatoly) Shcharansky as used in SOS advertisements (Box 35)
  - 4 oversize graphics design layout sheets for SOS advertisements, n.d. (Box 35)
- Photographs, 1977-1993
  69 prints, 2 color and black transparencies, 5 contact sheets, 1 negative and 8 negative sheets, 1 postcard, and 4 graphic design layout sheets depicting Elena Bonner, Kurt Gottfried, Andrei Sakharov, Natan (Anatoly) and Avital (Natalia) Shcharansky, Florence and Moris Pripstein, Andrew Sessler, Philip Siegelman, and others relating to the visit of the Sakharovs to Berkeley, Mrs. Shcharansky's visit to the Bay Area, and the Pripsteins' and others' visit to Moscow
  - 2 color and black transparencies of various sizes depicting Elena Bonner, Czeslaw Milosz, Morris Pripstein, and Andrew Sessler (Box 32, Folder 24)
  - 5 Contact sheets depicting Elena Bonner, Morris Pripstein, Andrew Sessler, and others (Box 32, Folder 25)
  - 1 negative depicting Andrei Sakharov, Yuri Orlov, and Natan (Anatoly) Shcharansky as used in SOS advertisements (Folder 26)
  - 3 prints of Andrei Sakharov, Yuri Orlov, and Natan (Anatoly) Shcharansky used for SOS advertisements (Box 32, Folder 27)
  - 15 prints of Morris Pripstein including 1 with Andrei Sakharov; 7 prints with others during SOS demonstration in San Francisco against A.M. Prokhorov in; 1 print with Andrei Sakharov and members of the SOS Executive Committee, including Robert Cahn, Kurt Gottfried, Philip Siegelman, and Bill Wenzel, at the residence of Efrem and Tatiana Yankelevich in 1 print with Andrei Sakharov and J. Hoffer, 1 print with Andrei Sakharov at New York Academy of Sciences with Morris Pripstein at the podium, 1 print with Elena Bonner, Florence Pripstein, and Andrei Sakharov at SOS reception in honor of the Sakharovs at Pripstein's home, and 1 print of Morris Pripstein in front of Sakharov home during Sakharov memorial, 1986 May 1988 November; 1988; 1988 November; 1988 summer; 1991 May (Folder 28)
  - 10 prints of Andrei Sakharov including 1 of himself in Moscow, and 2 of himself, 2 prints with Florence Pripstein at the SOS reception in Pripstein's home, 4 prints with Kurt Gottfried in Moscow, and 1 print of Florence Pripstein in front of Sakharov grave during memorial, 1979 September, 1980 February; 1989 summer; 1987 May; 1991 May (Folder 29)
  - 7 prints of Elena Bonner including 3 of herself in Moscow and 1 print with ? Gelfand,; 3 prints of Elena Bonner during her visit to Berkeley in with Morris Pripstein, Andrew Sessler, Charles Townes, with Joseph Cerny receiving a citation, and with a translator with Morris Pripstein at the podium, 1987 May 1990 March 1990 March (Folder 30)
  - 11 prints of Yuri Orlov including 3 of himself, print of himself, and 3 prints of himself, 1 print of Yuri Orlov at home of Gerson Goldhaber with Morris Pripstein and other members of SOS, 1990; 3 prints of Yuri Orlov with Morris Pripstein at Pripstein's home in Berkeley, n.d.; 1 1977, 1984 April; 1993 August (Folder 31)
  - 3 prints of Natan (Anatoly) Shcharansky, n.d. (Folder 32)
  - 3 prints of Avital (Natalia) Shcharansky, including 2 at the San Francisco Press Club with Owen Chamberlain, Don Glasser, Gerson Goldhaber, John McCarthy, Edwin McMillan, Emilio Segre, Morris Pripstein, Andrew Sessler, and Boris Gorbis (interpreter); and 1 print of Avital (Natalia) Shcharansky during her visit to Argonne National Laboratory with Malcolm Derrick and Mel Shochet, 1978 July (Folder 33)
  - 2 prints of an international tribunal in session, dealing with the case of Natan (Anatoly) Shcharansky who was serving a 13 year sentence on charges of treason, 1983 January 21. (Folder 34)
  - 9 prints of various individuals at the Postburd home in Moscow, including 4 prints of Kurt Gottfried with Orlov's son and others, 2 prints of Alex Ioffe, and 3 prints of Aber's son, Solomon Allen, Irina and Victor Brailovsky, and Paritsky, 1987 May (Folder 35)
  - 6 miscellany prints including 1 print of ? Gelfand in Moscow; 1 print of a plaque in front of Sakharov home in Moscow, n.d.; 1 print of Sakharov grave, n.d.; 3 unidentified prints; and 1 postcard depicting the Goddess of Democracy, n.d., 1987 May (Folder 36)
- Phonotape Cassettes, 1979 (Cassette cabinet)
  Three cassettes consisting of a SOS reply to an article in Pravda read by an unidentified person, a message from Alexander Lerner, and one of anti-Semitism
  - Reply from an unidentified person in SOS to an article in Pravda on the subjects of human rights in the Soviet Union and scientific exchanges between the United States and the Soviet Union. Includes a response to Soviet attacks on SOS activities (1)
  - Message from Alexander Lerner, expressing gratitude to Regina? and others who are fighting on behalf of the Soviet scientists. Includes Alexander Lerner's concern relating to his participation in the International Political Science conference to be held in Moscow, 1979 July, 1979 August 12-18 (2)
  - Anti-semitic preaching, n.d. (3)
- Videotape Cassettes, 1986-1990 (Tape cabinet)
  Twelve videotapes consisting of the interview of Natan (Anatoly) Shcharansky by Arno Penzias in Israel, Elena Bonner's speeches, at the University of California, Berkeley, on human rights and medical care in the Soviet Union, and news segments from various TV channels reporting on the political situation in the Soviet Union, an interview of Morris Pripstein following the death of Andrei Sakharov, and the visit of Elena Bonner to San Francisco to receive the United Nations award for human rights
  - Interview of Natan (Anatoly) Shcharansky by Arno A. Penzias on behalf of SOS at the University of Tel Aviv, with an introduction by David Horn. Includes a discussion about human rights issues, 1986 June 15. (1-4)
  - Abridged version of the interview of Natan (Anatoly) Shcharansky by Arno A. Penzias at the University of Tel Aviv, edited at the University of California, Berkeley, 1986 June 15. 1986 July 17 (5-6)
  - Shcharansky/Penzias interview, without any introduction, 1986 June 1. (7)
  - Elena Bonner's speech entitled "The Legacy of Andrei Sakharov: Human Rights and Politics in the 1990s" given at the University of California, Berkeley, Includes introduction and welcoming remarks by Morris Pripstein and Joseph Cerny, Dean and Provost, 1990 March 22. (8)
  - Elena Bonner's speech entitled "Health and Medical Care in the Soviet Union," given at the University of California, Berkeley, 1990 March 23 (9)
  - The McNeil Lehrer News Hour segment, on the political situation in the Soviet Union following the 1991 coup, Mikhail Gorbachev's promise to hold early elections and to quicken the pace of economic reforms, a demand for independence from the Baltic States, and George Bush's comments on the Baltic situation. Also mentions an interview with Elena Bonner and a discussion with four members of the United States Congress, Les Aspin, Patrick Leahy, Richard Lugar, and John McCain, on the impact of the political situation in the Soviet Union on United States policy (10)
  - KPIX Eyewitness News at Noon segment, n.d., consisting of a short interview of Morris Pripstein on on the occasion of the death of Andrei Sakharov, 1989 December 1. (11)
  - ABC News segment in which Elena Bonner speaks on the future of Russian democracy and expresses her support for the independence of Lithuania during her visit in the Bay Area on the occasion of her receiving the United Nations award in San Francisco for human rights (12)
- Incremental Materials, American Physical Society Sakharov prize speech by Morris Pripstein, 2010 (Box 32, Folder 37)